Guide to the Center for the Humanities Records 1974-2012
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
- Center for the Humanities - Operations, 1983-2012; Series V
  - Budget, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Autzen House - Proposal and Funding, 1988-1994 (Box 4)
  - Autzen House - Dedication, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Autzen House - Maintenance and Management, 1989-1997 (Box 4)
  - Humanities Film Collection, 1978-1996 (Box 4)
    Initiated by the Humanities Development Program, the Humanities Film Collection consisted of films either purchased or leased by the Center for Humanities and made available to OSU faculty for use in the classroom. A catalog of this collection was compiled by the Center for the Humanities and its films were organized into the following categories: Early Comedy, Silent Drama, The Thirties, Post-War Cinema, International New Waves, Experimental Film and Animation, and Documentaries. The collection's documentaries were further classified as: General, World War II, Religion, Third World, Americana, and Marine and Maritime.
  - Untitled lecture re: history of the Center for the Humanities, circa 1990 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings re: humanities at OSU and the Center for the Humanities, 1983-1990 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1984-1990; 15 images (Box 4)
    Photos include an image of Peter Copek conversing with Senator Bob Packwood at a press conference announcing the creation of the OSU Center for the Humanities; an image of the Autzen House facility; and images of Center fellows Michael Coolen, Rachelle McCabe and Don Morton [?]. File also includes two negatives of unidentified etchings.
- Center for the Humanities - Correspondence, 1974-2000; Series VI
  Series VI holds materials that document the Center's communications with fellowship applicants, invited speakers, internal stakeholders, and other humanities centers around the country. The series' General Correspondence files primarily focus on daily operations at the center. While the files in the series are dominated by correspondence, they also hold grant proposals made by other institutions/humanities centers and proposals made to funding organizations by the Center, as well as an array of newsletters, articles, curricula vitae, brochures, event posters and assorted background materials.
  - General Correspondence, 1983 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1984 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1985 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1986 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1987 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1988 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1990 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1991 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1993 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1994 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1995 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1996 (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Baker, Keith, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Birn, Raymond, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    File includes an audiocassette recording of a talk delivered by Birn at OSU, "Script Writing a Revolution: The Pamphlet Press and the Estates General of 1789," delivered February 22, 1989.
  - Bobo, Jacqueline, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Boise State University, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Bowling Green State University, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Burlington Northern Foundation, 1987 (Box 4)
  - California State University - Fresno, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Central Michigan University, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Central Oregon Community College, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Chambers, Doug, 1984-1987 (Box 4)
  - College of William and Mary in Virginia, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Collins Foundation, 1985-1988 (Box 4)
    File includes a proposal to the Collins Foundation for the funding of a building to house the OSU Center for the Humanities.
  - Consortium of Humanities Centers and Institutes, 1988-1999 (Box 5)
  - Cornell University, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Dobbs, Betty Jo, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Eaton, John, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Farrell, John, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Flaherty, Gloria, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Folger Institute, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Getty Trust, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Gilley, R. Stevens, 1985 (Box 5)
    File includes a proposal made to Gilley for endowment of the OSU Center for the Humanities.
  - Gordon, Kenneth, 1982-1989 (Box 5)
    File includes a monograph "Notes of a Naturalist: Poems and Drawings by Kenneth Gordon," published by the OSU Center for the Humanities, 1987.
  - Gustavus Adolphus College, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Hacker, Sally, 1978-1985 (Box 5)
  - Hacker, Sally - Memorial Fund Board, 1988-1995 (Box 5)
  - Hacking, Ian, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Harvard University, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Higgins Trust, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Holloway, Karla F.C., 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Hunter College, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Idaho Heritage, Inc., 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Jenkinson, Clay, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Kellogg Foundation, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Kelly, Petra, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Krause, Joseph, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Lafayette College, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Loyola University, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Lundeen, Robert, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
  - Mellon Foundation, 1983-1986 (Box 5)
  - Michigan State University, 1984-1988 (Box 5)
  - North Carolina State University, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Northwestern University, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Nowell-Smith, Geoffrey, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Oregon Committee for the Humanities, 1977-1989 (Box 5)
  - Oregon Council for the Humanities, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Oregon Marine Education Center, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Oregon State University - College of Liberal Arts, 1983-1989 (Box 5)
  - Oregon State University Foundation, 1980-2000 (Box 5)
  - Oregon State University - Foursight! Program, 1984-1996 (Box 5)
  - Oregon State University - Horning Endowment, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Oregon State University - Research Office, 1988-1998 (Box 5)
  - Organization of American Historians, circa 1982 (Box 5)
  - Rieckmann, Bill, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Robertson, Mary Elsie, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Rutgers University, 1988-1993 (Box 5)
  - Saddleback Community College, 1977 (Box 5)
  - St. Anselm's College, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
  - Snowman, Daniel, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Stanford University, 1986-1989 (Box 5)
  - State University of New York at Albany, 1974-1984 (Box 5)
  - State University of New York at Buffalo, 1994 (Box 5)
  - State University of New York at Stony Brook, 1986-1989 (Box 5)
  - Teter, Kenneth and Eunice, 1987 (Box 5)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1990 (Box 5)
  - University of California, Irvine, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - University of California, Los Angeles, 1984 (Box 5)
  - University of California, Santa Barbara, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - University of Chicago, 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 1984 (Box 6)
  - University of Iowa, 1995 (Box 6)
  - University of Kansas, 1984 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - University of Missouri - St. Louis, 1992 (Box 6)
  - University of North Carolina, 1983 (Box 6)
  - University of North Florida, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - University of Notre Dame, 1985 (Box 6)
  - University of Oklahoma, 1993-1995 (Box 6)
  - University of Oregon, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
  - University of Southern California, 1975-1984 (Box 6)
  - University of Utah, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - University of Washington, 1978-1988 (Box 6)
  - University of Wisconsin - Madison, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - University of Wisconsin - Milwaukee, 1981-1986 (Box 6)
  - Washburn University, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Wesleyan University, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Westfall, Richard, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Wheeler, Robert, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Williams, William Appleman, 1989 (Box 6)
    File includes a typescript "Controversy: Catalyst for Change," written by Williams circa 1989.
  - Wilson National Fellowship Foundation, 1990-1999 (Box 6)
  - Yale University, 1989 (Box 6)
- Center for the Humanities - Events, 1985-2000; Series VII
  Arranged into Series VII are materials related to numerous events, both large and small, that were either sponsored or co-sponsored by the Center. Primary among these events is the lecture series "The Constitution 1787-1987: Bicentennial Reflections," which brought nine different speakers to the OSU campus including Gore Vidal, who delivered the keynote address. The series likewise documents two music festivals, numerous symposia and colloquia, as well as an NEH-funded initiative for OSU faculty study of four non-western epics, as led by a series of invited experts.
  - Center Activities - General, 1985-1990 (Box 6)
    The "Center Activities - General" files include documentation of various activities sponsored by the Center for the Humanities, including Working Paper Series presentations and other seminars led by Center fellows, as well as film screenings, musical performances and other events co-sponsored by the Center in collaboration with various campus and community groups.
  - Center Activities - General, 1992-2000 (Box 6)
  - "Amadeus: The Life and Times of Mozart", 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    "Amadeus: The Life and Times of Mozart" was the title given to a two-month festival hosted in January-March 1986 on the OSU campus and elsewhere around Corvallis. The centerpiece of the festival consisted of six lecture-concerts and ancillary panel discussions focusing on Mozart's life, work and contemporaries. File includes a proposal to the Oregon Committee for the Humanities for funding of the event.
  - Promotional Photographs: "Amadeus: The Life and Times of Mozart", ca. 1985; 16 prints (Box 6)
    File includes black and white contact sheets and prints consisting primarily of images of OSU Music professor Tharald Borgir posing with a fortepiano. The file's contact sheets also include portraits of Mozart at various points in his life.
  - "200 Years of American Music", 1986-1987 (Box 6)
    Winter music festival presented at OSU in January-March 1987.
  - "The Constitution 1787-1987: Bicentennial Reflections", 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 6)
    A lecture series consisting of nine talks hosted by OSU in April-May, 1987. Files include a proposal to the John Ben Snow Memorial Trust for funding of the series.
  - Constitution Bicentennial Lecturer Files, 1986-1988; 3 folders (Box 6)
    In preparing for the "Bicentennial Reflections" lecture series, Center for the Humanities staff compiled folders for each conference speaker. These files included background information on the speaker, documents reflecting the logistics of their visits and stays in Corvallis, and materials related to the lectures that they delivered as participants in the series. The series speakers documented in these files are: George Anastaplo, Dwight G. Anderson, Carol Berkin, Lacy K. Ford, John Kaminski, Walter LaFeber, Tom Slaughter, Gore Vidal (keynote), and Sheldon Wolin. Files are also included for Stanley Katz, Stanley Kutler, Pauline Maier and Orde Pinckney, all of whom were invited to participate but did not do so.
  - Manuscript: "The Constitution 1787-1987: Bicentennial Reflections", 1989 (Box 6)
    A compilation of the presentations given under the sponsorship of the OSU lecture series bearing the same name. This manuscript was compiled with the hope that it be published in monograph form.
  - "Roots and Revolutions", 1987 (Box 6)
    Winter music festival presented at OSU in January-March 1988.
  - "The Military-Industrial Complex: Eisenhower's Warning Thirty Years Later", 1987-1988 (Box 6)
    Subtitled "An Interdisciplinary Conference on the Economic, Political, Social, Rhetorical and Technological Implications of the Military Industrial Complex," this event was held at OSU from October 13-15, 1988 and featured addresses by David Eisenhower, Johan Galtung and Seymour Melman.
  - "The French Revolution: 1789-1989" (Box 6)
    A series of six lectures presented at OSU from January-April, 1989. File includes a Project Director's Notebook documenting a performance by Clay Jenkinson titled "An Innocent Abroad: Thomas Jefferson in Paris," and supported by a grant from the Oregon Committee for the Humanities.
  - "The Epic Roots of Non-Western Literature: A Faculty Development Project." National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposal submitted by the OSU Center for the Humanities, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    This successful grant application supported the study, by fifteen OSU scholars, of four non-western epics in the company of "invited lead scholars of international repute."
  - "Cine-Lit: An International Conference on Spain's Literatures and Cinematographies", 1991-1993 (Box 7)
    A series of film screenings, round table discussions, and talks focusing on Spanish cinema, this event was held in Corvallis and Portland from February 27-March 3, 1991.
  - "Czechoslovakia, Bulgaria, Romania, and Yugoslavia: The Unbearable Past and the Uncertain Future", 1991-1992 (Box 7)
    A colloquium hosted by the Center for the Humanities on May 1, 1992 and featuring talks by John R. Lampe and Franjo Štiblar.
- Center for the Humanities - Fellows, 1987-2000; Series VIII
  Series VIII is comprised of internal and external fellowship proposals known or suspected to have been funded by the Center. Also included are a handful of proposals known to have been rejected by the Center but later accepted for funding when resubmitted in revised form. The series likewise holds a compendium of cumulative data documenting work done by Center fellows from 1986-1994.
  - Barbour, Richmond, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Beatty, Bess, 1987-1997 (Box 7)
  - Campbell, Courtney, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Carson, Mina, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Collins, Vicki, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Farber, Vreneli, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Fayad, Mona, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Gallagher, Sally, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Garcia, Kay, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Glenn, Cheryl, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Gray, Chris Hables, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Gross, Joan, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Guerrini, Anita, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Hackel, Heidi Brayman, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
  - Hanna, Susan, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Hart, Dianne Walta, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Kaatari, Stephen, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Keith, William, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Kesler, Linc, 1987-1990 (Box 7)
  - Knapp, Trischa, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Lee, Janet, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Leibowitz, Flo, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Lewis, Jon, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Lichtenstein, Nelson, 2000 (Box 7)
  - List, Peter, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Moore, Mark, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Oriard, Michael, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Osborne, Michael, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Petrov, Alexander, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Plotnitsky, Arkady, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Ramsey, Jeffry, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Robbins, William, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Robinson, David, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Roth, Barbara, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Sarasohn, Lisa, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Smith, Shannon, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Sonenberg, Maya, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Spanier, Sandra, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Stewart, Mart, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Unger, Frank, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Uzgalis, William, and Kathleen Dean Moore, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Wess, Robert, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Cumulative Data on the OSU Center for the Humanities Fellowship Program, 1994 (Box 7)
    File includes quantitative and qualitative data on the fellowship program, including number of fellowships awarded, publications and presentations resulting from fellowships, and end-of-stay reports written by various fellows. Most of the data cover the years 1986-1994; end-of-stay reports document work done by fellows in 1992-1993.
- International Film Series, 1977-1999; Series IX
  Founded in 1977 by Peter Copek and fellow English professor Anne Taylor, the International Film Series screened independent and foreign films every weekend during the term for over twenty years. Largely through Copek, the film series was administered by the Humanities Development Program and the Center for the Humanities for the duration of its existence. Series IX contains detailed documentation of the film series' operation, including the selection and screening of specific films, the proceeds (and deficits) accrued by the screenings, and the series' advertisement and impact on campus. Where appropriate, date ranges reflect activities conducted over the course of a given academic year.
  - Advertising, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Film Distribution Companies, 1988-1995 (Box 7)
  - Film Orders, 1988-1990 (Box 7)
  - Operating Procedures, 1986-1989 (Box 7)
  - Proceeds, 1981-1994 (Box 7)
  - Suggestions for Screening, 1986-1990 (Box 7)
  - IFS Operations, 1979-1984 (Box 7)
  - IFS Operations, 1988-1989 (Box 7)
  - IFS Operations, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - IFS Operations, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
  - IFS Operations, 1991-1992 (Box 7)
  - IFS Operations, 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - IFS Operations, 1993-1994 (Box 8)
  - IFS Operations, 1994-1995 (Box 8)
  - IFS Operations, 1995-1996 (Box 8)
  - IFS Operations, 1996-1997 (Box 8)
  - IFS Operations, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - IFS Operations, 1998-1999 (Box 8)
  - IFS Posters - 2nd to 11th seasons, 1978-1988 (Box 8)
  - IFS Posters - 12th to 21st seasons, 1989-1999 (Box 8)
  - IFS Flyers and Program Notes - 1st to 4th seasons, 1977-1982 (Box 8)
  - IFS Flyers and Program Notes - 5th to 7th seasons, 1982-1985 (Box 8)
  - IFS Flyers and Program Notes - 8th to 11th seasons, 1985-1989 (Box 8)